<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>systems — Savva Pistolas</title>
  <subtitle>Writing about AI, alignment, systems thinking, cybersecurity, futurism, privacy, and more.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/feeds/tags/systems/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/tag/systems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
  <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/tag/systems/</id>
  
  
  <updated>2026-03-02T11:31:41Z</updated>
  
  <author>
    <name>Savva Pistolas</name>
    <email>savva@pistolas.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Wage slaves: the Neo way</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/neo-robot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/neo-robot/</id>
    <published>2025-11-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-11-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The new neo robot premiered this week, showcasing the $500 a month subscription that sees customers gain access to a general purpose home robot. The thrust of the proposition is that the hardware is attached to a smart AI that can both carry out autonomous problem-solving tasks such as cleaning up the house, loading the dishwasher, and folding clothes. You have access to an app that allows you to schedule certain tasks, and the bot even has a ‘companion’ mode so that isolated but monied old folks have access to an embodied computation process to differentiate between cayenne and paprika.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/LTYMWadOW7c?si=bRKx8d2-KVxdrqSs&quot;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/a&gt; for some context on the presentation of the thing - I think there’s something so interesting about the approach taken for this. It’s quite a nostalgia driven advert that positions the main speaker as explaining the robot to his grandma - effectively placing the robot in the established present as something to be caught up with, rather than a new proposition to be thought over or weighed up. It was an impressive pitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New hardware for an old enemy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of course is that this is yet another massive smash and grab attempt on digital privacy in the global north, coupled with exploitation of the global south. First and foremost, all the popular media circulating of the bot shows the robot moving around home spaces inoffensively, inhuman in affect, but human in effect. The robot is however being teleoperated by someone using a virtual reality headset and controllers in almost all of the demonstrative media. While certain tasks (that are traditionally very easy for a human being to complete, but hard for a robot) can be given over to a problem solving AI, a lot of the activity that requires critical thinking and planning - such as cleaning an entire house, identifying and then taking out trash is actually intended to be handed over to a remote operator in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The clear and obvious definition of a fixed rate for unlimited human labour.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means you have access to unlimited human labour for $500 a month. This economy is deliverable only by providing a physical actuator for human labour in another country. Of course it would be illegal to ship over these workers and pay them their local domestic salaries in the global north to complete unlimited labour in the home day and night. Here then is one of the brazen value propositions of the Neo bot: We will make your domestic workers as fungible in form as you treat them to be in your mind’s eye. Interchangeable, dismissible, and inhuman. Abstraction of relational and eye-to-eye accountability is a key part of economies of scale in complex systems reliant on human labour, and this is no different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to presenting a complex challenge to labour law, this open approach is an evolution on the history of AI-centred organisations; historically, we have many examples of modern ‘mechanical Turks’ - that is, dressing up human labour as an AI application (Like Amazon’s ‘just walk out’ store which was actually staffed remotely by hundreds of Indian workers). Neo does away with the cloak and dagger, the system is open and indeed proud of its value proposition to the customer. Having produced a mechanism where instead of utilising the sustained efforts of one person, you instead tap into a managed pool of labour that can access the same physical actuation in your living room - Neo intends to sell wage slavery by the back door, abstracting your enjoyment of domestic bliss from the fleet of workers who provide it to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generally&lt;/strong&gt;, when people become wealthy enough that they own a space they cannot possibly maintain by themselves, they employ domestic workers. This is a complicated affair because domestic workers are people with souls and material needs, and likely exist in material conditions very different to that of the person wealthy enough to pay someone to tend to their home. This means that the wealthy are inherently suspicious and distrusting of their domestic workers, they think they will steal from them or live in resentment of their employer. The wealthy have to witness the worker, and worse than this - they have to witness the worker witness them. Neo is a sanitising solution; finally, we have access to the effects of domestic workers, without the human inputs or considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of all for the rich and suspicious: the sense organs afforded to the domestic worker to carry out their daily labour is a surveillance mechanism of their effectiveness and honesty. No more discretion, no more relationship, no more trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data nightmare on legs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The box-tee baseball-cap surfer-dude tech-bro who runs the wage labourer laundering company identifies a gender essentialising data model he calls ‘big sister’, which is where you admit that you’re a ‘big brother’ company but promise that you’re using the data to do good. It seems like the company has made it to a working teleoperational robot that can do a few things well, and aims to capture data from it’s first commercial user base to train it’s model over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to training off the manual labourers who perform domestic work via teleoperation (and building an incredibly valuable model most likely), this also means that your Neo bot is a data ingestion point, sucking up thousands of images of your home each day. The mind boggles at a future where law enforcement can get a floor plan of your house, or be let in at 2am by issuing a warrant to your domestic robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI has a central thrust of trading obscene amounts of compute that have clear and irreversible impacts on the climate - disproportionately effecting the global south. We have a rich and long standing tradition of exploiting the economic positioning of the people who live in poorer countries, which was leveraged as society digitalised to conduct labour at a distance - Indian call centres became a meme out of this frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last 10 years of efforts in the AI space have built a vehicle for ramping up efforts to sell consumer conveniences in the global north that are thinly veiled and mechanically abstracted outsourcing of thinking and doing to people in other countries - largely the global south. All of this incarnate and refreshed in Neo: The robot that proves that the venn diagram of people who like to brush wage slavery under the rug and think that doing the dishes is below them is a circle.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Agency claims from subjects in closed systems - Legalposting on social media</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/agency-claims-in-closed-systems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/agency-claims-in-closed-systems/</id>
    <published>2025-09-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-09-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>What cringe legalese facebook posts tell us about our relationship to exploitative data monopolies</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this about two years ago, and have been cleaning up my Obsidian vault in anticipation of a new academic venture that will require a lot of note taking… I came across this old self-blog and thought I’d host it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Stimulus&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;I was recently delivering a security awareness training session for a client&lt;/s&gt; &lt;em&gt;I was delivering a Security Awareness Training for a client in 2023&lt;/em&gt;, and was hit with a question that took me back to about 2015; &amp;quot;Sometimes you see those facebook posts that declare that you don’t give them permission to use your data and things like that - does that hold any water?&amp;quot;It blasted me back to when I would sit at my laptop as a 15 year old facebook user and see these armchair solicitors  - in very good faith, copy and paste viral statements regarding the new exploitation of your information by facebook or twitter, and attempt to opt-out of it with a legalese-ridden post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/dLyEQ4N.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other examples I could remember were just simple acts of attempting to withdraw consent to data capture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Hgraea4.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My answer to this question at the training was that there is no granularity in your consent when you use digital platforms that provide social media services, and if you have signed the EULA (Which is going to have been a requirement for you to access the platform), then the platform owner and team are the only ones who have a say in the exploitation of the information you provide them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there are settings that can be configured to alter or modify your privacy settings, but these almost entirely relate to how your data can be used or viewed by other third parties - the owner-operator of the platform has free reign with your data for the most part. There are currently some options to supposedly opt-out of the use of your data in training the AI models of certain platforms. When looking into this, I found that there was a new example of the legal-post phenomenon relating specifically to revoking access to your data for AI training:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/xyiKpCC.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Reflection&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users who feel that there is any chance of being able to directly modify the data relationship the given platform has to them by posting something are declaring something quite important; They declare that they believe they are able to use the bounded system provided by the platform to modify or escape the system itself. This signals a belief in the agency the user thinks they have to express themselves on the platform, and that they think this digitally enabled speech is equivalent to a public announcement or legal declaration. Quite confusingly, it really rather does declare that the user ought not to have their data exploited by the platform - because they can’t have made an informed decision to use the platform in the first place if they expect such a post to have any sort of impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also exposes that for the most part - we (as in people) still don’t understand the nuts and bolts of social media as a common-sense, and tend to treat it like a public commons or political sphere. Facebook is intuited by many as a digitisation of your persona for use with your professional and personal peer group. It is used to plan events, buy and sell, and make groups that mirror or imitate real world counterparts of such processes. These processes - in the real world, are defined by people’s participation, not by the platform of facilitation. We assume too readily that their digital and artificial counterparts provide the same core ‘features’ or ‘freedoms’. They do not. They are designed as a data service, and have no ‘social mandate’ outside of the fact that they’re being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The perceived experience from service users of social media that you are acting as your authentic ‘digital self’ on these platforms instead of accessing a locked-down and for-profit business platform shows how much educational work is needed to correct the ongoing social-media cultural campaign to convince users that they are “expressing themselves authentically” on their platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to quietly categorise the type of user who would post a “just to be safe” pseudo-legal notice as an older user, less understanding of technology and it’s mechanics - but of course this would be inaccurate. Younger users who have grown up in a post-explanatory consumer electronic landscape are using social media as a primary communication platform in their peer groups. Instagram and Snapchat are generally held in mind as ‘identity communication’ toolkits. While the campaigns to inform users of the impact of social media tends towards the social impacts, it may also be worth starting to look at educating users on how harmful it is to spend a majority of your social time on for-profit, data-driven platforms that seek to produce a service user that entirely understands their political or personal identity as a set of declarations, hosted (sponsored/mandated/permitted) by a tech company, with trips to the TikTok shop to make purchases acting as proof-of-identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average users are conditioned from the outset to build or produce a digital identity that relies on declaration - declarations of hobbies, interests, and ‘hot takes’. It may well be this hyper focus on the individuation of politicking in digital spaces that put such a focus on identity politics over materialism amongst onliners when they get into the real world. The whole shtick of social media is that you have been given permission to identify and express yourself on the platform, and need only declare who you are (the louder and more frequently the better) in order to successfully ‘be yourself’. The platform becomes the observer and mediator of identity claims in this case. Is it any wonder that this class of digital-first service users get a nasty shock when they discover the gilded cage they’ve found themselves in can’t be opened with the very same positivist identity claims the platform tells them they’re made up of?&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The new apple advert wants you to stop thinking about other people</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/apple-ad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/apple-ad/</id>
    <published>2025-03-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Septembers ad campaign that saw a formal invitation to truly stop thinking about the people we love.</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;h3&gt;This article is six months old&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this in September 2024, and simply never published it. It refers to an Apple ad campaign from September 2024. The focus still holds up as we continue to be served AI-driven features, so I decided to share it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shiny new Apple adverts work with Bella Ramsey to promote the ‘just-in-time’ wonder features made possible by ‘Apple Intelligence’, whereby the iPhone can utilise access to Ramsey’s data (her calendar, her email inbox, and her photo library) to avoid the realisation of an awkward or imperfect social moment. The best thing to do would be to go and watch the three examples before reading this, so here’s a link with each summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bella is at a party and sees someone across the room who she met at a meeting a few weeks ago but forgets his name; luckily, Bella can ask siri who she “went to that meeting with a couple of weeks ago” at a certain cafe. Siri reminds Bella who that meeting was scheduled with, and can greet Zach by his name as he sidles over.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bella is lunching with an agent who asks what she thought of the pitch she emailed over. Bella hasn’t read it and checks her phone, using the new “Summarise with AI” feature to read off a summary of the email and improvise a reaction. The agent reacts positively to this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bella is outside with her family; her mother, father, and younger sister (Kristy) stand surrounding the kid’s fresh grave for her pet fish. The father struggles awkwardly to improvise a eulogy. Luckily, Bella can ask her AI-assisted photo album to produce a custom photo album to music - using the prompt “Kristy with her fish, sad vibes”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the fact that Bella is rudely checking her phone in these interactions (or ducking behind a wall to avoid the gaze of Zach) - somewhat undermining the authenticity the ad is trying to sell us, the ad shines a light on the soft power campaigns I think we’ll see more of as AI continues to try and brand itself as a consumer solution, not a data nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Apple Way&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apple ecosystem is infamous for producing consumer electronics that work together with a continuity and convenience that improves in quality the more of their devices you add; similarly, Apple devices don’t play well with outsider devices, and it can be quite frustrating to use Android or Windows devices once you have become accustomed to “The Apple Way” of doing things. This design language teaches users that Apple sorts out the technicalities of computation, and that you get to experience the benefits of technology without any of the mechanics. This new advert takes these benefits into interpersonal interactions, and should be held in the same light as we examine what apple are trying to convince us is the line between the benefits of the social world and the cumbersome mechanics we must endure only until they can be automated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three adverts centre on the idea that there was a failing of some sort that has led to this moment, whether it’s the normal experience of forgetting someone’s name, or the absenteeism of modern tech-bro fathers everywhere in not paying attention to their children. Apple make clear that these moments are undesirable and ought to be done away with if at all possible. The premise is of course disagreeable; it is normal to find yourself forgetting someones name, it is equally as normal to be unprepared for a meeting. It is (sadly) normal for a parent to forget the things that their child find most interesting and engaging. With exception to the latter example, it is well understood that you just muddle through these moments best that you can, confronting the mild and impermanent anxiety that comes with this. You come out the other end a little sheepish, but otherwise unharmed. If you find those moments truly difficult, you pursue some behavioural or communicative improvement or strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the advert shows the opposite of this, that the need - or indeed the opportunity, for reflection is nerve-wracking, and is about to thankfully be made irrelevant. This AI feature is an augmentation of what we already behaviourally use smartphones for: quelling anxiety. Dead space and time is filled with scrolling of social media, you are never left alone or unoccupied, the thoughts or feelings of where you are and how you regulate that can be numbed immediately. There is no longer any need to be unstimulated. These social faux pas were a holdout against this flattened and flattening state of affairs - in the real world you can be pulled back into yourself and forced to confront your own understanding of reality when someone is brushing up against it in a way that isn’t immediately compartpentaliseable. The ad is communicating quite clearly that you can avoid these impure moments of a real and proper life from occurring if you take a bite of the apple, and they promise to make those twinging cringing moments melt away. In the case of the family - we are told that we can simply outsource these difficult moments to Apple (What are the priorities of this family that the nurturing of Kristy in a moment of sadness and learning ought to be outsourced to a consumer electronic? What a dismal and undesirable way of life; at the beginning of the advert Kristy had an inattentive father, by the end of it we had a demonstration that she had an inattentive family).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What then is the price of these features? Apple need to be able to make a sufficient enough digital twin of you that they can use it to feed actionable information back to you. This demands data. Data for the “you-machine”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Here’s the deal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple will facilitate this data-driven avoidant omnipotence if you ensure that you use an apple calendar, an apple mailbox, an apple phone, and apple storage. If you buy-in totally, then Apple can do the thinking and processing for you. This is very similar to the aforementioned design language of apple, save for one key difference: The scope. As mentioned, traditionally apple was focused on building an ecosystem of connected devices and services that don’t meaningfully interoperate with outsiders - shunning or disincentivising devices outside of their private ecosystem. This new AI approach ‘innovates’ on this and asks you to buy-in totally to an apple facilitated ‘lifestyle system’, shunning non-apple means of planning, chatting, photographing, calendaring, and beyond. If you decide to meet a friend next Tuesday, you ought to pop it into your iCalendar using a descriptive title (one that includes your friend’s name to tie them to the event), and don’t forget to include the name of the place you’re meeting. This voluntary reporting gives a copy of your plans to your iPhone so that is can use it to answer future queries and questions you may have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the opt-in that gives the phone sufficient data to produce and maintain a digital twin of you - one that contains live access to your plans, events, geo-tagged photos, notes, messages, etc. It is this that is probed in those moments to provide an unerring account of everything that you’ve ever done, everyone that you’ve ever seen, every message ever read. Where possible, these applications and services must all be Apple’s, the data must belong to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll be able to make better decisions about birthday presents for friends if you ensure the device has access to your entire conversation history, so you better make sure it’s on iMessage and not on Signal or WhatsApp. And don’t forget to sign in to your emails with Mail on Mac OS to ensure you never need to read another email properly again. Apple’s native journalling app can summarise your mood last week far more concisely than if you needed to leaf through your physical diary, so perhaps just commit to using that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the trade: Give them everything about you, so you don’t have to feel anxious about being yourself anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What future is this advertising?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of an awesome article written by Sam Kriss back in April - where he reflects on a month spent without his phone. He observed what came back to him when he stopped relying on his phone so much - the different shapes of the nerves and the thoughts that bubble up when you don’t have a constant reality escape hatch in the form of a connected device, and how this felt fruitful and whole for him:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A phone is a device for &lt;em&gt;muting the anxieties proper to being alive&lt;/em&gt;. This is what all its functions and features ultimately achieve: cameras deliver you from time, GPS abstracts you out of space, and an all-consuming screen that keeps you a constant safe distance from yourself. If there’s something you’re worried or upset about, you can simply hide behind your phone and it will all go away. One third of adults say they’re on their phones almost constantly. Their entire waking lives are spent &lt;em&gt;filling time&lt;/em&gt;, plastering over the gaps, burning up one day after another, waiting for something to happen, and it never does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full piece is well worth the read. This AI facilitated socialising is an extension of this &lt;em&gt;muting of the anxieties proper to being alive&lt;/em&gt; - AI intelligence will deliver us from interrelation with others as and when we see fit - expand that escape hatch to include our immediate interactions with others; I wonder about a future where this technology is completely metabolised into common use and what this means for us. Is it going to become rude or taboo when those of us who don’t adopt the technology continue to make human errors? Are 16 year olds going to do ‘networking prep’ on their mobile phones before going to parties, making sure that they’ve got suitable talking points and social contexts set straight with their device before rocking up to a house party? Exploring fully the impact this will have in peer groups, the problem scales quite quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on this, the system invites you to turn your friends into data-subjects; Zach doesn’t know that his whereabouts are being processed by some random device from inferred metadata, nor does young Kristy arguably even have the ability to offer informed consent to allow her likeness to be processed and collated by an AI - because she is a child. We’re being invited to literally capture more of our friends and relatives, to build a machine that ensures we know them and ourselves less and less. AI providers continue to cast these ethical questions by the wayside in an attempt to throw us irreversibly into a post-privacy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Zooming out&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of current media focus on the ecological and social impact that AI is having on the material world around us - ranging from the overuse of purified water to keep data centres cool, to the AI-enabled production and distribution of synthetic child sexual abuse material. AI also needs a lot of data to chew on to work effectively, and this data comes from our organic and semi-voluntary use of platforms that don’t give us a functional means to opt-out. This is combined with the flurry of boosterism from AI magnates such as Sam Altman who suggest that all we need to do to solve these problems is offer up more computational power, energy, and data until the AI itself proffers a solution. It’s a brazen strategy that asks us to step deeper into the flames to find the water - solve the data problem by giving it more data, solve the climate crisis by burning more of our fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apples new ad is an early example of what we’re bound to see more of; We’ll be offered consumer conveniences at cost to our data sovereignty, privacy, and authenticity of self. Apple are asking if we can be bought off while the VC-funded sprint to end the world the fastest carries on unchecked and unregulated.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pointing at the mushrooms - Identifying our own digital colonisation</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/mushroom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/mushroom/</id>
    <published>2025-03-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>A chat about digital advertising and fungus</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Far and away the most popular misconception I have heard about the way digital advertising works is that our phones listen to us and create tailored advertising based on this. It is a very accessible point of conversation for people who maybe don’t know the workings of the mechanisms that make their technology work but can use pattern recognition to identify their interests being presented back to them on their devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic story is always that someone was having a conversation with a friend (That was just incredibly specific and unrelated to what we would normally talk about) and then shortly after that the person received adverts that were tailored around the subject of conversation so specifically that the only logical conclusion is that the phone was listening to their conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While social media is objectively consuming your usage data to produce tailored advertisements - up to and including your message content, what you’re viewing, how you scroll, and who you’re talking to, it is not recording your voice in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from being an incredibly resource-intensive and impractical way to gather data that would be mostly pocket-noise, any recordings taken would be an observable action taken by software on your phone. Applications like facebook and instagram are constantly being researched and probed by security conscious researchers and hobbyists who are working to identify new ways that the social media giants are recording data on us. General audio recordings on your phone that capture conversation are not on these lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What then is happening? The answer is very much explainable by taking a left turn to talk about mycelium and mushrooms for a moment. Mycelium is the vegetative part of a fungus, consisting of a network of thread-like structures called hyphae. When a spore lands on a suitable ‘substrate’ they germinate and produce hyphae to ‘colonise the substrate’. This is where the hyphae consume the organic matter it’s attached to until the nutrient levels are completely depleted and the host is ‘saturated’ with the hyphae and mycelium. Once the substrate has been entirely drained of resources the fruiting body of the mycelium will form. The caps and stems we recognise as mushrooms are the fruiting bodies of these networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final and triumphant mushroom is our evidence that the substrate it sits in has been fully consumed by the underground mycelium. The mushroom is the output of an invisible process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, when we suggest that our phone ‘has to be listening to us’ to know our interests so well, we are only pointing at the mushroom. We have successfully identified the fruiting body of our total digital colonisation - but do not yet understand that the mycelium has taken root. We are the substrate and the fungus has successfully mapped and identified us, creating an accurate data profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This data profile (devastatingly) is sophisticated enough to begin predicting the conversations we may have, and who we may be having them with. Pointing at these adverts and suggesting that the phones are recording us is akin to pointing at a mushroom and suggesting we save the substrate. The substrate has been consumed, you are only observing the outcome.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People (myself included) have a tendency to think they are exempt from the workings of the machine, and that we are engaging sustainably with social media at a healthy distance. Sudden and unexpected accuracy of targeted advertising is a jarring reminder that this simply isn’t true. The moment of bafflement we experience when we look down and see such a precise marketisation of our own interests should always serve as a warning; We are the substrate! We have been successfully digitally colonised, the mushroom has bloomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be so much less worrisome if social media privacy abuse was as simple as recording you and spitting adverts back at you, but it is far more sophisticated and resource efficient than that. We are correct to assume that our phones ‘observe us’. It’s not using the microphone though, it’s certainly not ‘interacting’ with you, it’s just accepting everything that you’re offering up to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This observation is not a dialogic process, and not one that mimics a human conversation: you are simply being consumed. If you find that uncomfortable then you need to stop feeding the fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Anxiety alleviation rituals are not knowledge production</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/how-to-know/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/how-to-know/</id>
    <published>2024-11-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-11-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Reflections on the use of the term research and big data&#39;s attempts to innovate away the integrity of critical thinking</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Short reflection after reading: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2024/oct/27/for-my-son-ive-ceased-to-be-the-font-of-all-useful-knowledge&quot;&gt;For my son, I’ve ceased to be the font of all useful knowledge&lt;/a&gt; from the Grauniad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Do some research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term ‘research’ is always misused as to refer to ‘the collection of information to make or inform a decision or action’. When I am asked to put together a business case for a new tool at work, or decide where we ought to go for dinner next Tuesday, I suggest that “I do some research on the subject”. Of course this is not what research is; Research is the systematised work that aims to contribute to &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; stock of human knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say “&lt;strong&gt;The&lt;/strong&gt; stock of human knowledge”, we certainly don’t mean the bits of it you or I have experiential access to, we mean holistically and totally, totting up the knowledge that anybody and everybody has access too. If somebody knows about it already, then you are not doing research to find that information, you are just retrieving that information and making it known to yourself - further to the ‘research’ that produced it as knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/OyxEqDR.png&quot; alt=&quot;A flow chart showing the research object as a process of knowledge production, and the accessing of knowledge as information&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research is the process for a system of knowledge production, not the mechanism by which we make knowledge that exists available to ourselves. The use of the term research interchangeably with the action of information retrieval is symptomatic of a society that has a mostly individualised and individualising relationship with their information systems, where you equate what is known and knowable with what you (as an individual) know and can know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Digitalising how to know, providing what to know&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constant mix up on the term research is an insight into the lack of clear demarcation of &lt;strong&gt;research&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;information-retrieval&lt;/strong&gt; in what we could consider the ‘common sense’. In truth, the processes of research and the scientific method are our socio-cultural machine for ‘How to know’ something, with the resultant information produced being ‘What to know’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer electronics such as our kitchen-listener friend Alexa invite us to hand over our ownership of access to that mechanism of ‘How to know’ something to the Amazon Web Service; “Doing your own research” is now the act of submitting an information request to one of any number of monopolists who aggregate and present data (&lt;em&gt;selectively and in order of what is best for their advertising partners&lt;/em&gt;), and presenting that process as the effective mechanism for ‘How to know something’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further still the AI ‘revolution’ changes the landscape for users, with AI-powered summaries now ingesting multiple sources to produce an approximate summary of results (Google’s new Generative AI search results and Notebook LLM as relevant examples). What remnants there may have been of the behaviour to investigate and fully explore various sites or perspectives (Which is still not a true research method, but is designed to approximate one) is disincentivised - with your review of resources now automated, you get the information you need and a list of “sources” to the right. ‘How to know’ is obsolete, all praise ‘What to know’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/IDUTypP.png&quot; alt=&quot;A google result for &amp;quot;What is critical thinking&amp;quot;.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true mechanism of critical engagement and integrity of due process melt away into an anxious state of being for any participant of this new way of being and knowing; where knowing is not a habit of reflection or commitment to a process, but instead the perceived ability to - at any time, dip into the resource bank and access the offered information. Equally, to not know - is now simply to not be able to check your understanding of things against the relevant tool - a phone, a smart speaker, a search engine. Behaviourally, this leaves us with access to what we want to know, but no sense of authorship over the process that produced our understanding. Our relationship to this type of knowledge is an anxious one, where we defer from our faculties for learning and understanding, and foster a faith-based relationship to information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the digital information systems that people will use by default if subjected to broken-by-design devices that work to commodify knowledge and it’s access as data. It is profitable for providers to produce a relationship to knowledge that is owned and tended to by the devices they market as the true mechanism for how to know something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jettison of the need to have an explanatory, critical relationship with information is underway. It is systematised as normal and efficient to prioritise finding out “What you need to know”, with any process obsolete and time-consuming. Is it surprising that in this new world, a curious six year old may decide that it’s easier to skip the back-and-forth questioning with Dad, and simply get what he “needs to know” from the apparently superior source and digital childminder - &lt;a href=&quot;http://amazon.com/&quot;&gt;Amazon.com&lt;/a&gt; Inc?&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>smartphones and children</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/smartphones-and-children/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/smartphones-and-children/</id>
    <published>2024-09-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Reflecting on the landscape of children using smartphones</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; reflections after reading ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/23/children-who-dont-have-smartphones&quot;&gt;Only 3% of UK 12-year-olds don’t have a smartphone. Here is how four of them feel about it&lt;/a&gt;’ on the Grauniad. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we talk about smartphones and their impact we discuss the situation forgetting that “It is what it is” is actually “It is what the tech monopolists have spent billions making sure it is”. The smartphone itself is a wonderful tool that uses radio waves to send signals between endpoints in a rather vast network. The issue of course is going to be what is sent back and forth, and any mediums that exist in those spaces that have incentives outside of communication that mirrors or assists communication in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No more often is this evident than in the conversations had by adults about how children use technology. In these conversations, the smartphone is inseparable from the services it enables. You can’t fault people for bundling the two into one, as for most the former is simply the physical prerequisite for the latter. I am always struck by just how much compromise we have to make with these devices; if you want your child to be able to call for an ambulance, keep in touch with their friends digitally, be able to call you to let you know to come and pick them up, then you must also expect to fork over the right to access a large swathe of their developmental years to a digital monopolist who has a direct profit incentive to make them miserable, insecure, alienated, and unhealthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;internal behaviour between peers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These internal social behaviours and the digital spaces they occur in are not essential characteristics of the social lives of children, but instead the consequences of anti-social design. Snapchat and Instagram game-ify every single facet of communication, with scoring systems on every interaction, and a lack of accountability built into the platforms. This allows and encourages hit-and-run dopamine hits on your peers without suitable mechanisms for recognising harm, facilitating apologies and return to group wellbeing. They are systems that produce individuated and individuating young people, with no infrastructure for responsibility or collectivism in the software that enables the majority of their communication. In person communication then becomes a byproduct of their digital life, a reaction to the conversations spun up in broken-by-design apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;external influences on children&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally as egregious is the allowance for a child to be bombarded by consumerist forces as soon as they are given a device that facilitates the development of a digital identity. Advertisements baked into every single platform dictate to the child who they will fail to be until they look or act a certain way. Swamped in the individuating infrastructure of the modern internet, the only economy of change is in what you and yours buy, and how you and yours present it online. Influencers and other forms of soft-power serving global economic commercial interests spend more deep engaged, face-to-face time with children than their parents, embedding rhetoric that is not subject to accountability from fully developed adults, while ensuring a faith-like commitment to a set of ideals or ideas that are realised online but devoid of all authorship or critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;soft problems, hard solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issues with devices are not in their capabilities, but in the realisation of a technology that could be designed to enable and enhance the very best parts of childhood, subduing or challenging those difficult components that we wrestle with today. It is trivial to limit devices at the hardware level such that applications like snapchat and instagram are not usable without meaningful evasion and alteration from the user. Even then, a suitable logging mechanism can ensure accountability for such efforts. These apps and the men who make them have sat at our children’s table without asking, and they should be told to leave - quite as they would in the physical world. When we discuss ‘analogue’ parenting with our communities, we arrive at a consensus and make changes to our physical world to protect and empower our kids, and the same can be true for the digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ought to produce a mandate for the sanctity of childhood, and not let a commercial market for consumer electronics be metabolised as an unchangeable facet of the modern world that children must at some point be fed in to. It is quite possible to produce child-friendly electronics, and the project of doing so does not need to be one where snapchat gets to sit at the table.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Lapsus$ in judgement - The sacrifice of Arion Kurtaj</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/a-lapsus-in-judgement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/a-lapsus-in-judgement/</id>
    <published>2024-01-31T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>An examination of the recent Lapsus$ cyber attacks that culminated in the indefinite hospitalisation of 18 year-old Arion Kurtaj</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;As always, this website plays host to my opinions which are informed by my understanding of the facts available to me and the wisdom of the people around me. This article may be updated or amended in the event that new information comes to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a roster of attacks against Microsoft, Uber, Samsung, Nvidia, Ubisoft, and Rockstar Games, the Lapsus$ hacker group has become infamous for it’s outrageous smash and grab tactics that have impacted industry giants across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group’s members were, for a time, exclusively minors. They worked together on many majorly covered cyber offensives. The end of the story seems to be the indefinite hospital order placed on Arion Kurtaj - now turned 18, after he hacked Rockstar Games from within police protection at a Travelodge using an Amazon Firestick, a mobile phone, and the hotel TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news cycle has enjoyed sharing headlines expressing awe that a teenager could hack a huge organisation using such unorthodox and limited hardware. I would like to make some space to critically reflect on the veracity of these claims, and explore whether this hack really is the MacGyver mastermind hack that it’s being lauded as. Underlying this exploration will be considerations of the various structural and personal interests that might seek to oversell or ‘sex up’ this series of attacks from the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The group&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard of Lapsus$, here is a quick briefing on their activities:
Lapsus$ was a hackergroup based out of Brazil and the UK that was known for 11 major cyber attacks, all of which revolved around a similar modus operandi of gaining access to a corporate network by acquiring credentials from employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once credentials were acquired, the group could begin accessing the network. Having gained access, the attack was as simple as downloading whatever they could get their hands on; deleting the files on the client-side; declaring their triumph in a 50,000 member telegram group channel; and stipulating the terms of the extortion attempts against the organisation they had successfully targeted. That’s it. The reason the account of their methodology is so short is that it is simple and repeated. Lapsus$ don’t really know how to pick locks, they tend to just buy the key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group was comprised of seven people aged between 16 - 21, with the generally recognised leader being Arion Kurtaj - who was 16 when acting most prominently in the group. Arion has since been arrested and is currently on an indefinite hospital order. An additional 7 other members have been arrested by the City of London Police. A Brazilian citizen has also been arrested under the accusation of being a member of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the group was on their first major spree in 2022, I remember learning about the straight-forward nature of their attacks. Their process of accessing, exploiting, and extorting is actually quite a simple one. Despite the simplicity of the process, it nonetheless successfully attacked global giants like Nvidia, Samsung, Ubisoft, T-Mobile, Microsoft, and Uber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Described by &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://krebsonsecurity.com/2022/03/a-closer-look-at-the-lapsus-data-extortion-group/&quot;&gt;Krebs&lt;/a&gt; as “Low tech, high impact”, the Lapsus$ group employ solutions such as SIM swapping - where the attacker convinces a phone service carrier to switch a target SIM over to a new physical SIM to provide the ability to do text based multi-factor authentication. This, combined with an employees password, grants Lapsus$ access to their target network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’ll also happily just buy access to networks, purchasing access credentials from the internet, and also engage in plain old open recruitment on their telegram - saying they’re ready to pay employees to give them access to their corporate accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Picture1-623a2b2b62574.png&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of the Lapsus$ recruitment telegram messages as provided by Microsoft&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(Figure 1. Screenshot of an ad recruiting employees to give out access to their employer’s network from Microsoft’s “DEV-0537 criminal actor targeting organisations for data exfiltration and destruction”)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revenue stream to fund the acquisition of these access credentials is drawn from employing the same strategy on individual accounts at cryptocurrency exchanges.  The group likely use the SIM-swap method to access accounts and then drain holdings, in addition to any extortion payments made by their victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When access is acquired, the group don’t deploy malware or ransomware - which is what sophisticated threat actors might do to secure persistent access to the network for later use. Lapsus$ instead opt for what Microsoft classifies as “Exfiltration, destruction, and extortion”.  This is simply downloading everything that they can get their hands on and deleting it after the download completes. This dataset then forms the basis of their extortion attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, in their debrief on the tactics, techniques and procedures of Lapsus$, provide some interesting insights that involve light analysis on the strategy and behaviour of the group; one such insight is that there is a clear streak of apathy towards operational security or secrecy in Lapsus’ ranks, with very little effort made to protect the identities or ongoing operations of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Microsoft was actually able to stop the group from downloading source code during a live incident because Lapsus announced it to their telegram channel prematurely while the attack was ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group also enjoyed ‘embellishing’ the impact of their hacks to their channels. During their attack of security service provider Okta the group created and circulated strategic screenshots to lie about the extent of the systems they’ve compromised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the clearest indicator that the perpetrators were young and excitable, and not an advanced threat actor like a financially driven criminal organisation or state actor. The group are motivated by impressing and awing their audience, sometimes to the extent that they sabotage the entire operation by announcing it to 50,000 people halfway through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intelligence was quite unanimous quite early on that Lapsus$ were a group of teenagers utilising simple methods to conduct high-impact attacks, that manage to end up sabotaging themselves with their juvenile excitement. Furthermore, they argued with one another, as teenagers tend to - with the results being that Arion had his name and address leaked by one of his peers in his cyber circles. This is the behaviour being grandiosely characterised by Microsoft, one of their prominent targets, as a “unique blend of tradecraft”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft produced a 4,000 word incident response and threat intelligence report on the group in the wake of their hack on the company, naming Lapsus$ as the ‘DEV-0537 criminal actor’ or ‘Strawberry Tempest’ using their new weather themed threat intelligence taxonomy. They explored the group’s behaviour and threats, and did their best to take Lapsus’ claims to pieces. The main success for Lapsus$ came as Microsoft still allowed telephony-based MFA (recieving a text message to authenticate yourself instead of using an app like Microsoft Authenticator or Authy) and so it was with great ease that the group could exploit this using SIM swapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recommendation of avoiding using text messages for MFA was performatively publicised as guidance in the wake of the incident by Microsoft. This is a clear effort to make it appear as though we as a community are not already aware of this being best practice guidance that the giant was simply not following. Both the &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/setting-2-step-verification-2sv#section_5&quot;&gt;National Cyber Security Centre&lt;/a&gt; and the USA’s &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://pages.nist.gov/800-63-3/sp800-63b.html#multifactorOTP&quot;&gt;National Institute of Standards and Technology&lt;/a&gt; agree that telephony based MFA is inferior to other forms of MFA, and have done for quite a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always important to remember that anyone debriefing an incident response on their own organisation has a conflict of interest and is incentivised to make an incident appear as sophisticated as possible. To do any less is to admit the failure to prevent a simple attack succeeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For clients and share holders, it’s never going to be very reassuring to read a press release from a multinational conglomerate computing giant simply saying: “We still use text messages for MFA, and a 17 year old called up our SIM provider and convinced them to move one of our secure phone numbers over to a new SIM so he could log in”. Instead, the profit motive will have exerted a large amount of downward pressure on Microsoft’s editorialising of their debrief. To this end, the release is packed with melodramatic language and focuses on the impact of the devastating blow leveraged by the ‘Strawberry Tempest’ threat actor in the wake of their social engineering efforts to collect “intimate knowledge about employees, team structures, help desks, crisis response workflows, and supply chain relationships”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The last stand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we’re equipped with insight on the simplicity of the M.O. of Lapsus, and how their targets have been responding to their successful attempts to access their networks, we need to understand precisely how Arion conducted his infamous Rockstar Games hack. This will position us to assess how impressive it may or may not be and whether these Hollywood-esque headlines are being disingenuous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, Arion had access to a mobile phone - this is already enough to conduct the hack. Phones are just small computers, anything he had in addition to this will have been a bonus, but not a necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we remember the Lapsus$ calling card of purchasing or engineering access using employee credentials, Arion may have simply used existing credentials he had procured ahead of time. Alternatively, perhaps he needed to buy some and so hopped onto an access broker forum or telegram page and paid $40 for some user credentials using stolen cryptocurrency. When he did leverage his access to the network he began to download files, which is usually accomplished by right clicking and pressing download - not by ‘hacking the mainframe’. When he was happy with what he had acquired, he deleted the files on Rockstar’s side. Finally, Arion entered the Rockstar Slack channels to announce his hack and make his demands. It appears that no effort whatsoever was made to hide that it was him conducting the attack, or to secure the devices he was using. It’s worth remembering that he was committing these digitally enabled crimes whilst in police protection and supervision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s play with another theoretical - perhaps the police disabled the internet of Arion’s phone and so he was left without internet in the hotel room. The Amazon Firestick is another computer left in the room with him, it’s just got more controls and restrictions placed on it by Amazon. How difficult do we think it would be to remove these restrictions? This is called Jailbreaking or Rooting. It’s easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/8DURc7v.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A youtube search for &#39;rooting a firestick&#39;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks YouTube, looks like anywhere between 5 and 15 minutes if you don’t know what you’re doing. A Firestick is just running the mobile operating system Android, and reverting it back to this state allows us to install web browsers, and other tools. Perhaps Arion connected his phone via bluetooth to the Firestick to use it as a keyboard and mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of potential ways that this final outcome of Arion being digitally empowered to conduct this hack could have occurred, and none of them are particularly outlandish in terms of raw technical skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The duty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am left wondering why the police who have charge over a vulnerable young autistic man, who they deem to be an ongoing threat to the digital security of UK plc and it’s international friends, have left him alone in a hotel room with the exact hardware he needs to perpetrate another attack. We can see the lack of interest in operational security from Arion, we can also see Arion’s complete disinterest in the economic impact his hacks will have. Indeed, it is the intentions borne from this mental state that informed the decision to hold Arion in protection in a hotel. Why on earth did the police give a computer to the guy who said that he’ll hack again if given access to a computer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arion was actually deemed unfit to stand trial due to his severe autism, and it was this same mental health assessment that determined that he ‘continued to express the intent to return to cyber-crime as soon as possible’. His condition was legally recognised as affecting his decision making, to the extent that the court was directed not to assess his intentions when committing these offences, but simply whether or not he conducted the attacks. Arion has demonstrated time and time again that he may be unable to conceptualise the relationship between the actions that he is taking and the full impact of the legal consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With each hack, Arion must have been releasing a huge amount of dopamine, the neurotransmitter in our brain that relates to motivation and pleasure. It is precisely this identification of the dysregulation of dopamine that is observable in autistic patients and is currently being explored by some in the neuroscience community as a corresponding trait of Autism(&lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://www.jci.org/articles/view/127411&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://karger.com/dne/article/39/5/355/107836/A-Dopamine-Hypothesis-of-Autism-Spectrum-Disorder&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this conception, dopamine may be a substance to which Arion had a dysregulated relationship - and the safeguarding effort should have protected him from the medium by which he could suffer further from that dysregulation. In effect, the failure to remove digital technology from his room is akin to leaving a harmful substance proximate and accessible to a dependant user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the police did leave an internet-enabled computer in the room of a soon-to-be convicted cyber criminal, despite having a duty to prevent exactly that, then perhaps they might also see the benefit in avoiding commenting on the mundane simplicity of the hack and allowing the media to present it as the improvised miracle outcome of the machinations of a savant mastermind hell-bent on causing chaos and destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There would be a very clear benefit in avoiding the conversations about whether they checked the back of the hotel telly for a Firestick, or even whether they knew that this device counted as an internet-enabled device. That would raise all sorts of questions about whether the one safeguarding job they had was carried out properly in order to protect both the potential targets from being impacted, and the perpetrator from reoffending and hurting his chances of reform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is additional public interest in questioning if the training for safeguard assessments on these hotel rooms is sufficient, as not all digitally enabled crime is property damage. Police protection may apply to those engaged in harmful or violent imagery or communication, are these offenders offered the same opportunity to utilise internet enabled devices to further harm and be harmed by their behaviour? Perhaps this constitutes another reason to communicate that this incident could only occur if a technological whizz was at the helm of the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Incentive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police haven’t released the details on the hardware used in the Rockstar hack. Frankly they don’t need to, we have enough information based on the modus operandi of Lapsus$. All computers are still computers - regardless of their shape or size. Anything with internet access can be used to enter a username and a password, or browse the internet to buy illegal access credentials. That really is all there is to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very clearly possible to explain - with both brevity and the use of accessible language, that this was a security incident caused by a technically competent 18 year old who was using computers left in his possession to conduct a simple but high-impact attack. A considered approach, which journalists aiming to cover this story could utilise, would be to decompose the attack and contextualise it against the attackers history, as above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arion is now also a legal adult and so the press are permitted to print his name in their coverage. I don’t believe that the press coverage was at all informed by the investigative desire to understand or explain what happened, and this is clear in the absolute lack of technical detail or historical context shared by the press on Lapsus$’ behaviour. Outfits such as The Guardian have instead clearly opted for shock value, aiming to drive traffic to their sites and generate yet more noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This triple coincidence of wants amongst the private sector targets, the police, and the media shouldn’t go unarticulated. The private sector targets need to classify the attack as sophisticated so as to minimise impact on share prices or profit. The police maintain their credibility and public image by conveying the perpetrator as a mastermind. The media stand to benefit hugely from the exposure and traffic coming from a report on the latest Hollywood-esque hack coming from a minor. Allowing these organisations to benefit from and feed on the coincidence of these interests is an obfuscation of the moral duties at hand. We need to ask what the consequences will be for this young man’s life, and conclude that it is important to deconstruct these narratives when they emerge as an act of protection for people like Arion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this has adequately teased open a conversation about the finer points that may have been lost in the coverage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huge international organisations such as Microsoft and Rockstar that fail to take adequate steps to secure their systems against simple attacks can expect similar future incidents. Rockstar claims that the GTA 6 leak cost them $5 Million and “thousands of hours of staff time”, this was almost certainly about the voluntarily incurred marketing shift they launched to reexamine their strategy after the video game clips were leaked. It’s also worth mentioning that Rockstar’s notorious ‘crunch culture’ in which employees are culturally expected to work overtime 5 days a week means that Rockstar &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://www.gamerevolution.com/news/447299-rockstar-games-crunch-developer&quot;&gt;won’t be paying for hundreds of those extra hours anyway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are certain then, that this is not the last teenager who will successfully break into a large organisation in this way (Arion is certainly not the first), we must make a decision. Do we engage with these incidents like has been done with Lapsus$, or do we accept our moral responsibility to people like Arion who are vulnerable and need cultural and social support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would do well to understand that minors are only exercising the digital skills that come as a symptom of the world built around them by the very same organisations. A holistic and informed approach to the treatment of vulnerable people, who reach out and pluck the low hanging fruits of the digital world, would prioritise helping those individuals to avoid doing so in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am personally not bothered about bemoaning the impact of the damages to the brand of a game that lets you execute prostitutes and renames it’s likeness of a Vespa to a ‘Faggio’. Instead we would be better served by focusing on how we can assist the health and wellbeing of young netizens like Arion Kurtaj. Coverage of these incidents as anything other than this phenomenon is disingenuous and strips them of the advocacy and compassion that they are entitled to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can subscribe to my blog via &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://pistolas.co.uk/subscribe&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;tab:https://pistolas.co.uk/feed/&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to Eulalia Saurin, Androula Pistolas, and Elaine Haigh for your expertise, insights, and time spent on helping me produce this blog post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The internet forest</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/forest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/forest/</id>
    <published>2023-08-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;!-- PASTE VERBATIM POST BODY HERE --&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reflections on the radiowaves - TETRA:BURST and secure software in CNI.</title>
    <link href="https://pistolas.co.uk/tetraburst/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <id>https://pistolas.co.uk/tetraburst/</id>
    <published>2023-07-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;!-- PASTE VERBATIM POST BODY HERE --&gt;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
